Guide to the Buckminster Fuller's World Game: archive of original graphic art, film, video and audio media, manuscript material, and correspondence, from the files of Herbert and Mercedes Matter, ca. 1965-1980
Department of Special Collections
Buckminster Fuller's World Game: archive of original graphic art, film, video and audio media, manuscript material, and correspondence, from the files of Herbert and Mercedes Matter, ca. 1965-1980
M1378
Matter, Herbert
Matter, Mercedes
20 linear ft.
Stanford University. Libraries. Dept. of Special Collections and University Archives.
An archive consisting of approximately 500 items from Herbert and Mercedes Matter, including production files and original artwork, manuscript material, correspondence, film and magnetic media, photographs, books, and printed matter.
Access
Collection is open for research; materials must be requested at least 24 hours in advance of intended use.
Acquisition Information
The collection was purchased by Stanford University, Special Collections in 2003. Accession number: 2003-128
Biography / Administrative History
R. Buckminster Fuller conceived the World Game as an interactive role-playing experience that would teach participants to organize, revitalize and distribute depleted world resources. Relying on computers to provide raw data, players work non-competitively to allocate the earth?s natural capital worldwide, scoring points through efficient management. If cooperation degenerates into competition, the first step towards war, the game is lost. This archive documents the preparations for and execution of the inaugural World Game at the New York Studio School in 1969, which became a prototypical rehearsal for its 1971 appearance at the University of Southern Illinois. Born in Engelberg, Switzerland, Herbert Matter is best known for his international contributions in photography, photomontage, and graphic design work. Matter was also a filmmaker, exhibition designer, and professor. He came to the United States in 1936 and began work as a freelance photographer for Harper's Bazaar and Vogue magazines and the Museum of Modern Art in New York, and created displays for the Swiss and Corning Glass Pavilions for the 1939 World's Fair. He also directed, filmed, and edited Works of Calder in 1950 for the Museum of Modern Art, the first color film to show Alexander Calder's sculptures. While maintaining countless assignments, he introduced the first photography classes offered at Yale University where he taught until 1976. In 1943, Herbert married Mercedes de Cordoba and in 1964 she founded the New York Studio School of Painting and Sculpture (the Studio School). When the 1967 Montreal World?s Fair rejected R. Buckminster Fuller?s proposal to have the World Game played at the fair, Herbert and Mercedes offered to host him at the Studio School and offered the school?s student population for the inaugural World Game. Other related collections at Stanford University researchers should investigate would be the R. Buckminster Fuller papers (M1090) and the Herbert Matter papers (M1446).
Scope and Content of Collection
The collection consists of correspondence, manuscripts, photographs, artwork, videotapes, and publications.
Arrangement
Folder numbers consist of the "box number.folder number", e.g. "1.12." The collection is arranged in eight series:
Series I. Administrative Series II. Materials pertaining to the World Game class Series III. Promotional materials Series IV. H. Matter?s film on the World Game Series V. Photographs and negatives Series VI. Artwork Series VII. Publications and books Series VIII. Media
- Series 1:Administrative, This series contains materials the Matters collected pertaining to the administrative parts of the World Game class and the creation of a movie based on the class. The correspondence files contain letters from the Matters to R. Buckminster Fuller and from others to the Matters seeking more information on the World Game. A highlight would include the Matters' write up for Fuller's nomination for the Nobel Peace Prize. The series also contains biographical information on Fuller, budgets and receipts, and legal documents including the picture rights agreement between Herbert Matter and Fuller and a fundraising plan for the movie.
  - Correspondence, 1968-1980 (Box  1.1)
  - Correspondence from others (Box  1.2)
  - Biographical information on Fuller (Box  1.3)
  - Fuller Town Hall, New York, New York, Feb. 26, March 5 and March 12, 1971 (Box  1.4)
  - World Game budget and expenses (Box  1.5)
  - Invoices and receipts for film (Box  1.6)
  - Draft regarding fundraising for World Game film (Box  1.7)
  - Matter contract with Fuller (Box  1.8)
- Series 2: Materials pertaining to the World Game Class, This series contains documents pertaining to the preparations for and execution of the inaugural World Game in 1969. Documents include class roster, suggested reading list, the Matters brainstorming notes, transparencies.
  - Class information -- roster, reading list (Box  1.9)
  - Draft: agenda and schedule of World Game by Ed Schlossberg (Box  1.10)
  - Notes regarding the dynamics of playing the World Game (Box  1.11)
  - World Game Report -final and drafts (Box  1.12)
  - Unknown manuscript fragment -- could be RBF, "World Game how it came about" (Box  1.13)
  - Brainstorming notes (Box  2.1-2.3)
  - Transparencies used for World Game class (Box  7.1)
- Series 3: Promotional materials, Promotional and press materials for Fuller's World Game and internal documents Mercedes Matter created for the New York Studio School. Also included are notes and drafts of articles for publication in magazines specifically the Game and more broadly the scope of Fuller's work.
  - Miscelleanous notes, drafts of articles, press releases, promotional brochures (Box  2.4)
  - Handwritten drafts and notes for World Game article in newsletter (Box  2.5)
  - Layout for Ed Schlossberg's article (Box  2.6)
  - Typed report: "How to make the world work: a unique educational experience" (Box  2.7)
  - Drafts of New York Studio School's involvement in World Game (Box  2.8)
  - Drafts of July 1969 press release (Box  2.9)
  - Various drafts of typed paper entitled "World Game" for article in New York school newsletter by M. Matter (Box  2.9.1)
  - Notes and articles by M. Matter, flyers (Box  7.2)
  - Advertisement for Fuller's town hall speeches (first proofs) (Box  7.3)
  - Miscellaneous posters and mock ups of posters (Box  8.1)
  - Poster for town hall speeches, mock up for Alberto Giacometti exhibit, New York, 1974 (Box  8.2)
- Series 4: H. Matter's film on the World Game, This series contains the papers relating to Herbert Matter's documentation of the World Game which ran from June 12 to July 31, 1969. Records include print out of scripts and a narrative account from Matter on what inspired him to create the film.
  - Drafts "The World Game" and "Fuller Concepts Operative World Game" (Box  3.1)
  - Drafts by Herbert Matter on motivation behind film (Box  3.2)
  - Narrative account of World Game film (draft) (Box  3.3)
  - "Fuller July 28, 29, 30" (typed transcript) (Box  3.4)
  - Film script (typed draft) (Box  3.5)
  - Film roll 20 & 22 (typed draft) (Box  3.6)
  - Film Roll 6 (typed draft) (Box  3.7)
  - Typed document: "reels 1-8" (Box  4.1)
  - Typed document: "reels 9-16" (Box  4.2)
  - Typed document: "reels 17-23" (Box  4.3)
  - Typed document: "reels 24-28" (Box  4.4)
  - Typed document: "reels 29-34" (Box  4.5)
  - Typed document: "reels 35-41" (Box  4.6)
  - Typed document: "reels 42-46" (Box  4.7)
  - Typed document: "reels 47-52" (Box  4.8)
  - Miscellaneous mock ups of poster boards, credits, photo shots (Box  6.1.-6.3)
  - Draft of World Game on poster board (Box  1)
- Series 5: Photographs and negatives, This series contains various photographs, negatives, transparencies, slides and contact sheets related to Fuller and the World Game.
  - Miscellaneous negatives (Box  5.1-5.2)
  - Maps and charts of World Game, negatives (first choice) (Box  5.3)
  - Maps and charts, World Game, negatives (second choice) (Box  5.4.-5.5)
  - "Maps to enlarge", black and white photographs and negatives (Box  5.6)
  - Contact sheets (Box  5.7)
  - Miscellaneous photographs (Box  5.8.-5.9)
  - Oversize photographs (Box  Flat box 9.6.-9.10)
  - Oversize photographs (Box  Flat box 12.1.-12.7)
- Series 6: Artwork, This series contains Matter's original artwork, collages, sketches, paste-ups, proof sheets, and mechanicals, relating to posters, catalogues, media advertising and exhibition displays for the World Game.
  - Miscellaneous artwork, drawings and posters (Box  8.3.-8.5)
  - Miscellaneous artwork drawings and posters (Box  9.1.-9.5)
- Series 7: Publications and books, This series contains publications from the Matters' reference library. Box 10 contains publications that solely deal with the developments of mankind's voyage to the moon. Box 11 contains publications that highlight Fuller's work and the World Game and box 13 contains various clippings. Various books were removed to the Rare Books division and catalogued individually.
  - The New York Times. 1 August 1969. Vol CXVIII, No. 40,732. (Box  10.1)
  - Newsweek. 11 August 1969. "Moonwalk in Color." (Box  10.2)
  - Look. "Apollo 8: Voyage to the Moon." By the staff of The New York Times. (Box  10.3)
  - Look. "Apollo 11: On the Moon." By the staff of The New York Times. 15 July 1969. (Box  10.4)
  - Life, Special Edition. "To the Moon and Back." 1969. (Box  10.5)
  - Life. "Barnstorming the Moon." 6 June 1969. (Box  10.6)
  - Life. "The View From the Moon." Vol 46, No. 1. (Box  10.7)
  - Life. "The Incredible Year '68." 10 January 1969. (Box  10.8)
  - Life. "On the Moon." 8 August 1969. (Box  10.9)
  - Life. "Johnny Carson: The Lonesome Hero of Middle America." 23 January 1970. (Box  10.10)
  - Life. "The Cruel Dilemmas of Duty." 7 February 1969. (Box  10.11)
  - Life. "Off to the Moon." 4 July 1969. (Box  10.12)
  - The New York Times. "The Moon: A New Frontier." 3 August 1969. (Box  10.13)
  - Life. "Our Moon Trip." 22 August 1969. (Box  10.14)
  - Life. "Leaving For the Moon." 25 July 1969. (Box  10.15)
  - Life. "Our Journey to the Moon."17 January 1969. (Box  10.16)
  - The New Yorker. 8 Jan 1966. New York Studio School of Drawing, Painting and Sculpture, Inc. (Box  11.1)
  - Art News. September 1952. Schwabacher-Frey. (Box  11.2)
  - "Design of Alternative Futures" Syllabus. Jon Dieges, 1969. (Box  11.3)
  - "About Crystal Consciousness: Involvement in Building Curvicostate." Keith Critchlow. (Box  11.4)
  - "Universal Requirements Check List." Buckminster Fuller. Reprinted from "Architectural Design" March 1960. (Box  11.5)
  - Saturday Review. "Education Reform 1957-67: It Didn't Start with Sputnik." 16 Sept 1967. (Box  11.6)
  - Architectural Forum: The Magazine of Building. August 1951. (Box  11.7)
  - Architectural Design. Reprinted from the July 1961 issue. (Box  11.8)
  - Time. 2 February 1970. 2 Copies. (Box  11.9)
  - The New York Times. "Automation House." 1 Feb 1970. (Box  11.10)
  - Life. "The Inauguration: Rhetoric Meets Reality." 31 Jan 1969. (Box  11.11)
  - "Ecological Surveys from Space." National Aeronautics and Space Administration. Washington D.C. (Box  11.12)
  - "Vertical is to Live--Horizontal is to Die." R. Buckminster Fuller. Reprinted from The American Scholar, Vol. 39, Number 1, Winter 1969-70. (Box  11.13)
  - The New Journal. "Can Bucky Fuller or Clem Markert Save the World Before Ed Logue Destroys It?" Vol. 2, #11. 11 May 1969. (Box  11.14)
  - "The World Game." R. Buckminster Fuller. 18 June 1969. Joint National Meeting of the American Astronautical Society and the Operations Research Society. (Box  11.15)
  - Whole Earth Catalog. "The World Game." March. (Box  11.16)
  - "50 Yeas of the Design Science Revolution and the World Game." R. Buckminster Fuller. Southern Illinois University. 4 Copies. (Box  11.17)
  - Miscellaneous clippings (Box  13)
- Series 8: Media, This series includes the ten hour film segments Matter created documenting the World Game.
  - Buckminster Fuller, "Bucky Balls", Kodak Videocassette, N/A (Box  14.1)
  - Buckminster Fuller, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, Jan. 29 1969 Part 1 (Box  14.2)
  - Buckminster Fuller, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, Jan. 29 1969 Part 3 (Box  14.3)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll G), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 16, [1969]" (Box  14.4)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll I), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 23, [1969]" (Box  14.5)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll 6), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 24, [1969]" (Box  14.6)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll 5), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 24, [1969]" (Box  14.7)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll E), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 13, [1969]" (Box  14.8)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll D), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 13, [1969]" (Box  14.9)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll C), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 12, [1969]" (Box  14.10)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll B) r, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 12, [1969]" (Box  14.11)
  ,
  - Buckminster Fuller, "B. Fuller Talk - Tails Out" - Camera B - Film Roll 1, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape (Box  14.12)
  - Buckminster Fuller, "B. Fuller Talk - Tails Out" - Camera A - Film Roll 2, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape (Box  14.13)
  - Buckminster Fuller, "B. Fuller Talk - Tails Out" - Camera B - Film Roll 3, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape (Box  14.14)
  - Buckminster Fuller, "B. Fuller Talk - Tails Out" - Camera A - Film Roll 4, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape (Box  14.15)
  - Buckminster Fuller, "B. Fuller Talk - Tails Out" - Camera B - Film Roll 5, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape (Box  14.16)
  - Buckminster Fuller, Leo Steinberg, Helical Scan Tape, V-32, 3/2/1973 (Box  14.17)
  - Buckminster Fuller, Studio School, Helical Scan Tape (2 tapes), V-30 H, NY Studio School 5/2/74 (Box  14.18)
  - Buckminster Fuller, R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape-tape 3, V-32, "dub from old format to new 1/2" (Box  14.19)
  - Buckminster Fuller, R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape--tape 3, V-32, "dub from old format to new 1/2" (Box  14.20)
  - Buckminster Fuller, R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape--tape 5, V-32, "dub from old format to new 1/2" (Box  14.21)
  - Buckminster Fuller, R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape--tape 4, V-32, "dub from old format to new 1/2" (Box  14.22)
  - Buckminster Fuller, Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, Jan. 29 1969 Part 2 (Box  15.1)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll J), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 23, [1969]" (Box  15.2)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll H), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 16, [1969]" (Box  15.3)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll A), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, 12-Jun-69 (Box  15.4)
  - Buckminster Fuller, (sound roll F), Scotch brand. 20 1/4 Inch Tape, "June 13, [1969]" (Box  15.5)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, No title (Box  15.6)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, "Synergy Map, Electromagnetic Spectrum" (Box  15.7)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, No title (Box  15.8)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, "Garden of Eden, Naga" (Box  15.9)
  - R. Buckminster Fulle, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, "Definition of World Game, Man's Function in Universe" (Box  15.10)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, No title (Box  15.11)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, Worldgame (Box  15.12)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, (Poor Recording) (Box  15.13)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, "Playing Worldgame, Energy Network" (Box  15.14)
  - R. Buckminster Fuller, Helical Scan Tape, V-30 H, No title (Box  15.15)